Resume Preparation

WHAT IS A RESUME?

A resume is a summary of your education, experience and skills for potential employers. The resume's physical appearance, and more importantly, what you say and how you say it, will affect an employer's decision to interview you. Your resume should highlight your qualifications for employment in a particular position or career field. A resume prepared for one position might leave out information that would be included in a resume for another position. In all cases, your resume should focus on your qualifications and transferable skills, and suggest future contributions you could make to the employer.

Your resume should always be up-to-date, so rewrite and reprint as often as necessary- in fact, it is a good idea to update your resume every time you have a new accomplishment or credential. Keep in mind that your resume may get as little as 15- 30 seconds of consideration. Be relevant, concise, and consistent in your layout and writing style. Always remember, resumes get interview, not jobs!

CHECKLIST

Use this before asking someone to critique your resume for you.

- **Most Important Info First-** Everything on your resume should be written with the most important information first. Consider this when choosing the order of sections after the Objective.
- **Reverse Chronological Order-** Within each section, each entry should be arranged with the most recent experience first.
- **Relevant to Objective-** When you're trying to decide what to leave in and what to leave out, make certain that everything relates back to your Objective. Also, make sure that your descriptions highlight and accentuate the connection to your Objective.
- **Meet the Employer's Needs-** (academic, experience, leadership)- Everything on your resume should communicate to the reader that you know what the employer's needs are and that you have the experience, skills, leadership and education to meet employer's needs.
- **Be Professional-** When people seek an entry-level position, they are generally trying to bridge the gap between student and professional. You can accomplish this by keeping out or changing the items which remind people that you are student (high school education/activities, listing dates by semester rather than month, listing many "interests").
- **Consistency-** Everything from dates to abbreviations and formatting should remain consistent throughout your resume.
- **Past Tense-** Use past tense action words to demonstrate the transferrable skills you can offer the employer.
- No Pronouns
- **Sentence Fragments-** Employers look for short, direct pieces of information. If it is too long or overly descriptive, people may choose to skip it.
- Include Skills, Memberships, etc.
- PROOFREAD!
- **Contact the CRC-** You can make an appointment or drop by for more assistance.



Sample Resumes

Alberta Lagator

LinkedIn.com/in/albertlagator 1234 Archer Road #56 Gainesville, FL 32608 ALagator@ufl.edu

To obtain a full-time position as a study abroad adviser at the University of Florida that utilizes my organizational, creative, and interpersonal skills.

EDUCATION

University of Florida, Gainesville, FL Bachelor of Arts in French

Minor: Statistics

Relevant Coursework- Regression Analysis, Theory of Interest, Design of Experiments, Introduction to Probability

UF Paris Research Center - Summer Interdisciplinary Studies (Language and Culture)

June - July 2013

August 2013 - Present

University of Florida Paris Research Center, Paris, France

Career Ambassador, University of Florida Career Resource Center

- Conducted mock interviews and critiques of résumés, cover letters, and personal statements written by University of Florida students on an individual basis
- Advised students on topics such as choosing a major or career, finding a job or internship, and applying to graduate school Presented information about Career Resource Center programs and services to classes and student organizations
- May August 2013 Foreign Language Partner, English Language Institute Paris, France
- Engaged in one-on-one conversations with international students to help them improve their master of the English language
 - Provided tutoring to partners in their English Composition and Literature classes Gained a greater understanding of the French language

UF French Club: Le Cercle Français

Director of Public Relations

Created and distributed fliers on campus to attract new members

August 2012 - Present

August 2012 - Present

- Maintained the club's Web presence utilizing social media platforms such as Facebook and Twitter Collaborated with the club's Historian to publish videos and photos on the club's website

Volunteered at French Club's community events to help raise community awareness of Francophone cultures Participated in weekly round-table discussions to actively maintain spoken French skills

AWARDS & AFFILIATIONS

Member, Golden Key International Honour Society Member, University of Florida Honors Program Recipient, Anderson Scholarship

Languages: French (Fluent), Haitian Creole (Conversational), Spanish (Basic)
Computer: SAS/STAT; MATLAB; Microsoft Word, Publisher, Excel, and PowerPoint;
Certification: Microsoft Office Specialist: Microsoft Office Excel 2013

Albert Gator

albertgator@gmail.com ● J. Wayne Reitz Union ● Gainesville, Florida 32611 ● 352.392.1601

OBJECTIVE

Seeking a summer Aerospace Engineering internship where I may use my engineering background and my interpersonal skills to further company growth and develop professionally

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science in Aerospace Engineering University of Florida, Gainesville, FL

May 2017

GPA: 3.81/4.00

Computer: AutoCAD (Beginner), SAP (Beginner), LabVIEW (Intermediate), SolidWorks (Intermediate), Excel (Intermediate) TECHNICAL SKILLS

Intern, The Boeing Company Seattle, WA

WORK EXPERIENCE

May 2015

• Developed tool to track Undefinitized Contracts in an effort to increase transparency of organization with regards to future work

June 2013 - August 2013

- Worked with buyers and engineers to support perfect product delivery by tracking "late to need" and "past due" parts
 - Assisted SCA's in accomplishing their day to day tasks allowing for a greater level of efficiency on an individual basis

January 2013 - Present Assistant Project Manager, BF Productions Miami, FL

- Remedied mechanical, electrical, and communication errors efficiently under extreme time constraints
- Set-up and operated equipment worth between \$2,500-\$5,000
- Directed successful multi-thousand dollar events for high end clientele
- Managed all entertainment aspects of events with an average of 100 guests

Cashier, Publix Super Markets Inc.

August 2012 - Present

Gainesville, FL

Ensured customer satisfaction in a continuous fast paced environment

- Counseled newly hired employees to effectively accomplish their respective duties
- Calculated cash balances to maintain consistent financial records at the end of each shift

PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Design Competition, TropiCHOMP Transition Program Gainesville, FL

July 2012 - August 2014

- Identified and solved mechanical weaknesses of a number of other team's robots upon completion of personal robot.
- Directed a team of 4 focused on designing a personable, remote controlled robotic toy for around 15 sick children in Shands Hospital in under 3 weeks

Director, "Keeping Yourself Grounded" College of Engineering Event

March 2013 – April 2014

- Planned an event for the entire College of Engineering focused on helping engineering students de-stress before finals and
 - providing tips on dealing with the most common challenges of being an engineering student Directed over 30 people
 - Responsible for coordinating the attendance of accomplished speakers for the event

LEADERSHIP

President, Rho Omega Rho Fraternity

September 2013 - Present

May 2012

August 2014 - Present

August 2014 - Present

- Allocated an annual budget of \$25,000 to five committees for alumni and philanthropic events Cooperated with 10 other executive board members to ensure proper procedures
 - Increased membership by 10% reaching out to incoming freshman students

Member, Freshman Leadership Engineering Group

 Planned, organized, and helped run an event for Freshman Engineering students aimed at promoting retention; the event was a September 2012 - May 2013

- success with well over 200 students attending
 - Developed tools and methods to increase membership and motivation for the organization

SKILLS

Languages: Spanish (Fluent), French (Conversational), Mandarin (Basic)

options. The format and content of a resume will change depending on the objective and amount of experience. A resume is a strategic document. The resumes above are samples providing possible formatting and content